<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sutton's synagogue, or, The English centurion shewing the vnparallelled bounty of Protestant piety / by Perci. Burrell ...</title>
            <author>Burrell, Percival.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4126.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S258</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22160934</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22160934</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25198</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17283)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25198)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1747:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sutton's synagogue, or, The English centurion shewing the vnparallelled bounty of Protestant piety / by Perci. Burrell ...</title>
                  <author>Burrell, Percival.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 25 [i.e. 27] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T.C. for Ralph Mabb,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed [at] London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1629]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.) and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A² B-D⁴ E².</note>
                  <note>A sermon commemorating Thomas Sutton's founding of Charterhouse.</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 26-27 misnumbered 24-25.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sutton, Thomas, 1532-1611.</term>
               <term>Charterhouse (London, England) --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke VII, 5 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25198:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SUTTON'S SYNAGOGVE <hi>OR,</hi> THE ENGLISH <hi>CENT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RJON:</hi> Shewing the vnparrallelled bounty <hi>of Proteſtant piety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY PERCI. BVRRELL, Preacher at King IAMES his Hoſpitall in the Charterhouſe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Euſeb. lib. 8. c. 12. de Prae. Euan.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concurritur ad loca ſacra, quae dicuntur Synagogae.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 112.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The iuſt ſhall be had in euerlaſting remembrance.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>T.C.</hi> for <hi>Ralph Mabb.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25198:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25198:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Reuerend Father in God, the Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> his Grace, To the Right Honourable, Right <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend, and Right Worthy Gouernors</hi> of King IAMES his Hoſpitall, my <hi>moſt freely noble, and euer</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Patrons, Grace and Glory multiplied.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt Reuerend, and Right Honorable.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>As Temples are conſecrated to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our great God, ſo Bookes ſhould bee dedicated to good men, becauſe both haue Altars of intended ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and gratitude. To your wiſedome did
<pb facs="tcp:25198:3"/> our Founder commend his ſtate; at your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours feet J lay downe theſe dreſsings of his memory:<note place="margin">Debui quod po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, non potut quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Aug. ep. <hi>28.</hi> Hier.</note> Theſe fruits of a thankfull ſoule, for my free admiſsion into the Charterhouſe, and my freely obtained preſentation to a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice, may the Fonuders wealth ouerſhadow his Preachers pouerty. Certes the pious mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence of famous <hi>Sutton,</hi> is a great orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to our deceaſed King of bleſſed memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, a greater to this age, the greateſt to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant religion. Jf J for his ſake may hope for any fauour, Turne in (my Lords) turne in, and let thouſands follow, while your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipps behold, and diſpoſe That beautifull Chappell, thoſe well furniſhed Chambers, thoſe tables, thoſe gownes, thoſe bookes, our memorable Founder hath purchaſed, for ſuch aged men, and hopefull children, whoſe duty it is to petition the Lord of Lords for the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and eternall happineſſe of you our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious &amp; happy Gouernors, among thoſe knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humble, and deuoted Seruant in the Lord, PERCI. BVRRELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25198:3"/>
            <head>Suttons Synagogue: OR, <hi>The Engliſh Centurion.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVKE. 7.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He hath built vs a Synagogue.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nniuerſarie Commemorations of Magnificent Founders, are as wch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ned Inſtruments to ſound the prayſes of the Deceaſed, and as goodly Monuments to commend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto Poſteritie the Gratitude of the Liuing. Exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>len<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Father;<note n="a" place="margin">Monumenta mem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>is mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>a. <hi>Aug de C. D. li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> c 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Solemnities are not ſuperſtitions Sacrifices, but pious Records:<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctanus D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> So that as <hi>Toxaris</hi> to <hi>Menippus</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Annuall honours done to <hi>Pylades,</hi> I may preface to you of this firſt Stone, or vnpoliſhed Pillar, rayſed or intended to our SVTTONS honour. We doe by Statute celebrate the memorie of our vnparallel'd Founder: Not to Canonize him for a Saint, but to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite an imitation of his bleſſed Magnificence. For as<note n="c" place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ptorum an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ad San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dun <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. <hi>Aug. vbi ſuper.</hi>
               </note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath obſerued, To commend the Bountie of the Dead, is to ſpurre vp the Liberalitie of the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuing. Wherefore at length, Awake Organ &amp; Voyce, Old-men and Children, Prieſt and People, Awake:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25198:4"/> Let vs offer the ſweet incenſe of zealous thankes vnto that God who hath appointed his Steward <hi>Sutton</hi> to be a nurſing Father to the aged, whoſe ſtate, or bodies haue beene maimed by bearing Armes, and as a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Mother, to maintaine youth in the acquiring of Arts: To this end are wee aſſembled this day, to this end hath <hi>Sutton</hi> rayſed this Synagogue; I muſt haue this day no other Theme, you ſhal heare no other note, but <hi>Sutton</hi> hath built vs a Synagogue, <hi>He hath built vs a Synagogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Difficile est abijs diligi, quos dignitate anteceſſerit. Hier ep. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note>It is a point of high difficulty, and therefore of greater honour, to purchaſe loue of thoſe who are out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhined by vs in eminent dignity: yet, this can bounty and gentleneſſe effect; for behold, our Centurion, (whoſe office it was, to bridle the inſolencies of the mutinous <hi>Iewes,</hi> and to ranke them in obedience to the Roman State) euen our Captaine enioyeth fauour, and receiueth honour from a ſtifenecked, proud, and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious nation. The Elders expreſſe the reaſon in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of this verſe; <hi>He loueth our Nation.</hi> Loue can command loue, and charity like fire can melt ſoules frozen in peruerſneſſe, or like the Adamamant can attract hard, and ferreous ſpirits: for ſee, the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> tender to the well fare of our Centurions Grome, and thoſe incredulous <hi>Iewes,</hi> who ſcorned to petition Ieſus for the ſaluation of their owne ſoules, are zealous Aduocates for the corporall health of the Centurions Seruant: the ſtrongeſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue they conceiue for the reparation of the temple of the ſeruants body, is the commemoration of the Maſters piety in erecting a Temple, or building a Synag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gue to the honour of God: ſo my Text. <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th built vs a Synagogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:25198:4"/>
            <p>Herein ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the
<list>
                  <item>1. Noble Founder.
<list>
                        <item>1. Office, or title, a <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion,</hi> this an honorable title.</item>
                        <item>2. Worke, a ſtrange work, a Centurion, a <hi>Builder.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. Expedition, <hi>Hee hath built.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Sacred foundation.
<list>
                        <item>1. Temple, <hi>a Synagogue.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. Templers, a whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>for vs.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The founder, Hee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hee,</hi> who? is the man of magnificent piete? a <hi>Nehemia</hi> with a ſword in one hand, and a Synagogue in the other; hee who hath merited the character, of<note n="f" place="margin">Dicier hic est</note> The man, the founder: <hi>He,</hi> a Centurion, a Captaine of an hundred, but the chiefeſt among thouſands: <hi>Hee,</hi> that C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>taine whoſe honour it was to haue his Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in <hi>Capern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> the metrapolis of <hi>Galile,</hi> and which is more, the City of the great King:<note n="g" place="margin">Centurio Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus, &amp; ipſe ſructut ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Chryſ st. ſer. <hi>102.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He,</hi> that good Centurion, the ground of whoſe heart anſwered the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of our heauenly husbandman, with the happy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of an hundred fold; <hi>He, he</hi> was that Souldier, who did as well follow the Lord of Hoaſts, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand men: <hi>He, he</hi> who was valiant in the field, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute in the Temple.<note n="h" place="margin">Quis non diligat eum, qui ſub palu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damento mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari, opera agat prophta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum? Hiero.</note> Oh let vs admire, honour, and loue that Captaine, who in the habit of a Martiall man, performed more then the office of a Prophet required: Here is a Captaine worthy to lead the whole Chriſtian world, for he loued the people of God, and built a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue for the God of all people.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Altenigina generatione, demeſticus operatione princep. mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſocius Angelorum. <hi>Orig. in Math</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>He,</hi> a Roman by generation, by regeneration a Saint; by nation an alien from the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by faith a Sonne of <hi>Abraham,</hi> a Captaine ouer men, a Peere of Angels. The leſſe his profeſſion did promiſe,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25198:5"/> the greater is the honour of his deuotion: the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſpo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>en, and ruine Cities; but this Captaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>richeth God, and buildeth Synagogues.</p>
            <p>The Church muſt bee placed vpon a high Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that all nations may behold her glory and fly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, but in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his holy march, Captaines muſt bring vp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Vanitie, mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ary men muſt be leaders; nor may this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſt ange, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>athers, and they will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>u, that a So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>er and a Saint may haue but one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: ſo as not <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, a mili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>? was not <hi>Dauid</hi> a Souldier, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>phet or a King? did not hee rayſe that Temple in his heart, which was after finiſhed by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;, 4.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat ſhall I more ſay? <hi>For the time would faile me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll you of Ioſhua, of Gidion, and of Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, of Ah<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z, and Iehoſaphat, who ſubdued King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es, waxed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in fight, put to flight the armies of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iens, conquered themſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and did not onely ere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Altars <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o, but we e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uing Temples of the Lord? If you looke into the Goſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Luke 3.14.</note> you may obſerue the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier a more a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tentiue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>itor of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bbie; after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he aſcenſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, you may behold a moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>minent Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Corneli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 10.2.</note> 
               <hi>He was a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout man, and one tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>red God withall his houſe, hee g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue much almes to the peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and prayed God alway:</hi> if we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>call Hiſtories, wee ſhall finde the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>s, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n: <hi>Iulians</hi> thundring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gion, <hi>Conſtanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Great, and the victorious as well as pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Theod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he zeale and faith of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ethe S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne of God with admiration,<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uſtine</hi> ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eth, Chriſt did<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> admire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is, com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nd the piet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our Captaine: thus we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt.</p>
            <p>If r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ted to diſcourſe of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>et one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould diuine, hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rdinall vertue, but a principall, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>undam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntall grace; therefore Chriſt entitled a <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25198:5"/> the ſtrong man,</hi> in one word, he who was a Lambe for me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, was alſo a L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n for courage: but it may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you are tyred with following our Centurion, therefore I ſhall now intreat him to come home to you with an application.</p>
            <p>Here we learne, Saints may beare Armes,<note place="margin">An obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning warrs.</note> and they who beare Armes may be Saints: warre is not vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, where the cauſe of warre is iuſt: cowardly and cruell is that opinion of Anabaptiſticall ſpirits, which condemneth warre, and damneth the Souldier, for as<note n="l" place="margin">Christiana d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſciplin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bella n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> culpat om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. ep. 5, <hi>Mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>llino.</hi>
               </note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>guſtine,</hi> Chriſtian religion doth not prohibit all warres: elegantty<note n="m" place="margin">Nihi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants nocet ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>theus. ep.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ierome,</hi> The Souldiers belt is no enemy to the ſword of the Spirit; the coate of mayle no ſuper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as to the breſt-plate of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; nor the head-piece of ſteele, any obſtacle to the helmet of ſaluation: heare<note n="n" place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendere tit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorum eſt non religioſorum. contra Fauſt. <hi>Mani. c. 74.</hi>
               </note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> againe, What is the crime? what is the greateſt miſery of warre? by an honourable death in the field, to preuent a foule, at beſt a more painefull death amidſt perſonate mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in a Chamber? Vpon this ground to cenſure the military profeſſion, is a character rather of a Coward, then a Saint. Take away the hunger of rapine, the thirſt of reuenge, and the boundleſſe deſire of inlarging do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, A Chriſtian may with as ſafe a conſcience be a Souldier, as a Miniſter: Thus wee ſee a Centurion ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be a Saint.</p>
            <p>Againe, Oh that all Souldiers,<note place="margin">The applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> did march vnder our Centurions colours, for then ſhall Kingdomes be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and Martiall affaires proſper, when deuout men are Souldiers, or Soldiers are deuout men; but alas what hopes of vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, when, as the Armies encounter an Enemie, ſo Souldiers warre againſt God, and the cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and vnrepented ſinnes of the people fight againſt the Souldi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>? All hiſtories are plentifull in this point, and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> maketh it a rule,<note place="margin">Ep. 82.</note> that the ſinne of the Souldier, ſharpeneth the Sword of the Enemy: there was a time when the euening was a prophet to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25198:6"/> day, <hi>Haralds</hi> troopes imployed their laſt night in reuellings, and laſciuiouſneſſe, but the companies of <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Normandie,</hi> did bleſſe their deſignes with prayers and faſting, and ſo became conquerers, <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah, Ahaz,</hi> and <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> went from the Temple to the field, or rather made the field as a Temple, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they proued triumphant, not ſo much by fighting againſt Man, as by humbling their ſoules before the Lord of hoaſts:<note place="margin">K. Charles.</note> bleſſed be our <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> who hath commanded faſting and humiliation to bee as the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds of his no leſſe iuſt, then neceſſary warres, this point ſhall end in a ſhort eiaculation, O thou God of battails, arme our forces with truth, meekeneſſe, and righteouſneſſe, then ſhall their hands doe terrible things, and their feet ſhall tread vpon the necks, of thy Goſpels, our gratious Kings, and theſe Kingdomes Enemies.</p>
            <p>The Centurion hath put off his Armor, and now beginneth to <hi>build,</hi> here is the ſecond branch, <hi>building,</hi> He hath <hi>Built.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ. in 1. Cor. 3.</note>Building muſt accompanie faith, and in this one word of building, we ſhall finde the ſeuerall furnitures, roomes, and ſtoaries of all the duties of Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the Apoſtle is plaine, Let all things be done to <hi>edification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Caeleste adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium diſpere gendo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruitur. <hi>Gr. M. hom. 37.</hi>
               </note>There is an euident difference, betweene celeſtiall, and terreſtiall buildings; terrene houſes are raiſed by collecting, heauenly manſions are framed by diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting monies, and we may coniecture that our incarnate <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> was pleaſed to bee the putative Sonne of a Carpenter, that as Chriſt was, ſo each good Chriſtian ſhould endeauour to be an holy builder.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:25198:6"/>
            <p>In goodly buildings we muſt finde.
<list>
                  <item>A foundation, This is Chriſt, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, the life giuing, the chiefe corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, the foundation of foundations; here the builder vpholdeth the worke, or rather is the baſis of his owne ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture: would you ſee how Chriſt was ſquared and adapted for this edifice? obſerue thoſe no leſſe buſie, then cruell labourers, his ſtony-hearted tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; the rods were as the Maſons bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, the croſſe the forme whereon they carue, and hew their ſtones, their hands the mallets, the nailes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thornes, and ſpeare, the ſeuerall tooles to poliſh, and fit this ſtone for a foundation vnto our heauenly Manſion.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The maine Pillar, Hope, the Wals Charity, the Cement the Word preached, the Windows Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the Roofe Faith.</p>
            <p>For the Furniture, the moſt conuenient Hangings, are meditations vpon our Sauiours Paſſion, Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, and his glorious returne to iudgement: the Chayres and Beds, are Loue; the ſeuerall vtenſiles, or other ornaments, are Meekeneſſe, Temperance, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>There is a ſentence no leſſe famous then difficult con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the materials of this building, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13. the Fathers are diuided in their diſpute, whither this place concerne the doctrine of the Preacher, or the conuerſation of the Auditor:<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> is firme for the latter, him I follow, while he writeth, that this text doth point at the actions of Chriſtians. now read the words. <hi>If any man build vpon this foundation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>Gold, Siluer, Pretious ſtones, Wood, Hay, Stuble, euery mans worke ſhall be made manifeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gold, Siluer, Pretious ſtones,]</hi> theſe are ſolid,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Caietane. in 1 Cor. 3.</note> glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and high prized vertues. Gold, the loue of God;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25198:7"/> Siluer, charity to man; Pretious ſtones, theſe are the ſeuerall acts of piety toward God, and mercy toward man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wood, Hay, Stuble,]</hi> by theſe are figured, dangerous ſinnes; Wood is the wormes neſt of corroding enuy, or malice. Hay, is ambition; Stuble, this is the type of obſtinate ſchiſmaticks;<note place="margin">verſe 15.</note> now followeth the knot, the maine difficulty: <hi>if any mans worke be burnt, he ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer loſſe, but he himſelfe ſhall be Saued;</hi> but this ſauing is equall with damning, ſo<note n="t" place="margin">Ambr. in 1 Cor. 3 Chryſoſt. in eundem locum</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> he ſhall bee ſaued by fire; his body and his ſoule ſhall not bee waſted by the torments of hell; S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> proueth, what S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> affirmeth: <hi>That is ſaid ſometime, to bee ſaued, which is not conſumed, as gold in the fire, as the liuer in the fable, this this indeed, is the hell of hels, death without death, and torments without conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: leaſt this might ſeeme ſtrange,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforceth his argument, with an excellent obſeruation from Scripture language: <hi>It is the elegance of ſacred rhetoricke, to giue gentle names to ſeuere puniſhments, as hell and the graue, are called the places where all things are forgotten,</hi> which at the firſt view may promiſe quiet and the obliuion of all calamities: thus the death of the wicked is termed a ſleepe, thus it is ſaid of the wicked,<note place="margin">Iob 21.33.</note> 
               <hi>That the clods of the earth ſhall bee ſweete vnto him; here is moſt bitter and desperate ſweetneſſe:</hi> the ſame Father ſhall conclude<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſoſt.</note> hee that buildeth with Hay or Stuble, ſhall continue in endleſſe torment. Apply.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Application.</note> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care, eſt ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> embu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note>He buildeth moſt fairly, who liueth moſt religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: pluck therefore the hand out of the boſome, worke and build: the beſt approbation of our faith, ariſeth from the operation of the hand; as the curious Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, ſo the religious Chriſtian, muſt be knowne by his handy worl e; diuinely <hi>Irenaeus</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d feris lucet, in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, &amp; quod intus eſt fori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> luceat. <hi>Irenaeus lib. 4.</hi>
               </note> Let your charity burne within, and holineſſe ſhine without; by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer you ſhall auoyd hypocriſie, by the latter idleneſſ
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25198:7"/> You muſt all bee builders, God is the Maſter of the worke, all the Sonnes of men, King, Prieſt, and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, muſt be labourers. Birds make their neſts, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſts ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ir d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s; let men build houſes, let th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſting habi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, <hi>Make you friends of the vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Mammon, that ye may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> receiued into euerla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting habitations:</hi> let vs heare the Sermon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Dauid</hi> to his Princes, <hi>Set your heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cron. 22.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>and your ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to ſeeke the Lord your God, Ari e and build: As liuely ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nes, come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> liuing ſton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>that</hi> (ſince you cannot build of yourſe ues) <hi>you may be built vp as a ſpiritual houſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coptab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Christ.</hi> I ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l end with t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Lord Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us build vs all together for an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of God through the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pirit,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We haue a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ady ſeene our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ounder, as a Captaine, and a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der; now behold him like a Cherubim, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith winges ouer his hands; this you may finde in his</p>
            <p>Expedition, he <hi>Hath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the Eagle ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eth to the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, or the greedy Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>poyle, ſo our Centurion to the moſt noble acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> piety,<note n="a" place="margin">Plu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imum tu omni re ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as. Sene. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. ib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> ſure our leader was one of the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>res:</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d it was his honour, for where the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igious, there <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> his march is moſt glorious, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>dition muſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ncere, Vo en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s &amp; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in all c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions, the reaſon is euident: C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rity is a faire char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſincerity, and a quic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hand is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing ſigne of a willing heart. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> into the family of <hi>Abraham,</hi> you ſhall read h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>artineſſe in nim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes: Firſt <hi>Abraham</hi> runneth in per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n to meet the Angels,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.2, 6, &amp; 7.</note> then hee charged <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ah</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o make read quickly, then he runneth againe to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rd, laſtly the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruant is as quicke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe; thus we ſee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruant, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Abra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ms</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he performance of any ſeruice vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God: I wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, is but a large comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and we know thoſe to bee moſt ſlow in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, who are nim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e in promiſe; ſweet and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25198:8"/> is the memory of this Founder, He did not frame a Colledge in the paper modell of a litigious will, but ſaw a Synagogue rayſed at his owne proper charge to the glory of God: ſo the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ders, he <hi>Hath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The innocent Doue hath a nimble wing, ſo thoſe good ſoules which are quickned with that Spirit, who once appeared in the forme of a Doue, flee ſpedily vnto workes of piety; the Sunne cannot ſo much reioyce to runne his courſe, as the faithfull to conſummate their race of Godlines; the elements, of fire, aire, &amp; water, are actiue and quicke in their motions, ſo where ſoeuer the holy fire of zeale, the water of ſanctification, or the breath of the Spirit are found, there is a ſpeedy moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: nay euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dul &amp; lazy earth is moued with an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.21. Act. 9.36.</note> but no terror can ſtirre the earthly minded man; the bleſſing of <hi>Nephthali</hi> was to haue the ſwift feete of a Hind, <hi>Dorcas</hi> was as nimble as the Roe:<note n="c" place="margin">Vtinam pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centa famina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum imitaren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur viri. Hier.</note> Oh that good men would imitate the ſpeed of this woman: <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be not ſlacke in thy buſineſſe,</hi> I beſeech you be not ſlow in the buſines of the Lord:<note place="margin">Prou. 10.26. Leuit. 11.41.</note> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ſnayles, wormes, and creeping creatures were bani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hed from the Altar of God, to inſtruct vs, that ſlow paced men can be no pleaſing ſacrifice for our God.</p>
            <p>To ſpurre vp our deuotion, let vs conſider, that God is pleaſed to pay magnificently for the expedition of man: Mans expedition, and Gods ſaluation embrace each other; for no ſooner can the deuout ſoule ſay, <hi>I haue</hi> kept the faith,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.7.</note> but hee may read, Henceforth a crowne of righteouſneſſe is layd vp for thee; no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner can our Sauiour proclaime, I haue fulfilled the will of God, but a voyce is heard from heauen, <hi>This is my beloued Sonne:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 9.35.</note> nor is God more indulgent to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Sonne of his boſome, then to the zealous, and his adopted ſonnes among the children of men; for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue,<note place="margin">Matth. 19.28</note> doth <hi>Peter</hi> come vnto our Sauiour and ſay, <hi>Wee haue left all and followed thee?</hi> the bleſſing is annexed, <hi>You ſhall ſit on thrones in the kingdome of heauen:</hi> Nay
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25198:8"/> but impatient incredulity muſt haue ſome-what in hand, what would you expect? will you bee content with a thouſand for one hundred? this is more then extortion dare challenge, yet the ſpeedy ſoule ſhall haue more, euen one hundred for one;<note place="margin">Matth. 19.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>one hundred for one,</hi> not of corruptible gold, but in the incorruptible treaſure of peace of conſcience, and the ſweet aſſurance of heauenly happineſſe: Remember <hi>Zacheus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 19.9.</note> doth hee come quickly to entertaine the Sonne of God? the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell is, <hi>This day is ſaluation come to his houſe:</hi> excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Quam ſuaue mihi ſubito carere pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cati ſua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tatibus. Aug. Confeſ.</note> Oh What a heauen of ioy is it to be a penitent ſoule, heartily and ſpedily to loath the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonning ſweet of bewitching ſinnes? oh then all you who haue that good ambition to bee married vnto the Lambe of God, take into your ſoules, the prayer of the Spouſe, <hi>Draw vs oh Ieſus and we ſhall run after thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Apply, When drunken <hi>Archias</hi> receiued intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,<note place="margin">Plut. Pelopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das.</note> of treaſon plotted againſt his Maieſty by <hi>Pelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidas,</hi> be ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmerd forth this reply, <hi>Great matters to morrow,</hi> and ſo became a prophet of his owne ruine: are not moſt of vs of the Court of <hi>Archias?</hi> when the conſcionable Miniſter informeth vs of the damnable ſtratagems of Sathan againſt our ſoules, we ordinarily conclude, Great matters to morrow, hereafter may be ſoone enough. When vnhappy <hi>Faelix</hi> heard S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Sermon of temperance and iudgement to come,<note place="margin">Act. 24.25.</note> hee trembled indeed, but his concluſion was, <hi>Go thy wayes for this time, I will heare thee at ſome more conuenient leaſure,</hi> thus while the preacher is in the pulpit, a fit of deuotion may be raiſed in the ſoule of the Auditor, but reſolutions of holineſſe muſt bee put off to ſome other time: ſo that as cheating and bankrupt debtors anſwer their creditors, ſo moſt men reply vnto the Spirit,<note place="margin">Matth, 22.5.</note> come to morrow, or ſome other time: <hi>I haue bought a farme, I haue marryed a wife;</hi> profit or pleaſure muſt be obſerued, God muſt wayt.<note place="margin">Pro. 3.28.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon</hi> aduiſeth <hi>not to hold a friend in ſuspence till to morrow:</hi> Oh bee not leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectfull
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25198:9"/> of thy God, then thou wouldſt bee of thy friend. That good God who hath promiſed ſaluation to him who ſhall repent at any time, hath bound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to no time of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayting for thy repentance.</p>
            <p>Wee may read of an hereticall brood, which were called <hi>Clinici,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Centur.</note> their deuotions were like themſelues bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid; they would neuer thinke of a new life, before they were in the iawes of death. The whole world is of their faction, for ſcarſe any thinke of being holy, or doing good, vntill there be no hope of being. Delay in matters of greater moment is accounted dangerous: in the aſſuring of our ſaluation, by the holineſſe of our conuerſation, procraſtination may proue damnable; the feet and the heart were Gods part of each ſacrifice, the heart for ſincerity,<note place="margin">Leuit. 1.9.</note> and the feet for celerity. If you could conſider the greatneſſe of your iourney, euen from earth to heauen: and the ſhortneſſe of your life, which is called a vaper,<note place="margin">Iames. 4.14.</note> that appeareth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſurely you would gird vp the lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s of your minde, <hi>and runne with faith and patience the race that is ſet before you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> I beſeech you mocke not God, cheat not your owne ſoules, with the hopes of a panegyricall, or commendatory Sermon ouer your hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, or with the legacy of an ambitious doale at your funerall, but while you read this poore meditation, pray that this may be the houre of your conuerſion, a liuing ſacrifice, or the ſacrifice of the liuing is moſt acceptable vnto the Lord.<note place="margin">Ier. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>Oh Ieruſalem waſh thy heart from iniquity, when ſhall it once bee?</hi> I haue done with the Founder: now let vs ſuruey, the ſacred foundation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond generall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Synagogue]</hi> The Temper of the Founder is beſt diſcouered in the foundation: the ambition of <hi>Pompei,</hi> and the luxury of <hi>Lucullus,</hi> were preſented to the view of all, by their ſtately buildings; but our good Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will haue no other Monument of his glory, but a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25198:9"/> place where the honour of God may dwell, a <hi>Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is the mother and roote of our <hi>Synagogue,</hi> and hath two daughters, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the former doth commend vnto vs either the aſſembly of men in the ſeruice of God,<note place="margin">Caſaubonus exercit. ad An. Bar. 16.</note> or the vnion of the ſoule with God by the participation of the bleſſed Euchariſt, thus the viſible Church is ſtiled, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Baſil. M. in Pſal. 28.</note> a viſible collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or congregation of men, thus alſo, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of the ſoule vnto God, as the members are to the head. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Synagogue</hi> was a place conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated for the aſſembling of men to prayſe, and call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the name of God.</p>
            <p>There were three eſpeciall places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Iews</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhip of God.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The <hi>Temple,</hi> here were prayers, ſacrifices, and ſermons.</item>
               <item>2 The <hi>Synagogue,</hi> here were pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, &amp; ſermons, but no ſacrifice.</item>
               <item>3 The <hi>Schooles,</hi> here neither pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, nor ſacrifices, but lectures and diſputations.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The glorious <hi>Temple</hi> was the Cathedrall or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church, the <hi>Synagogue</hi> as the Chappell of eaſe: it is obſerued that for one <hi>Temple,</hi> there were 480 <hi>Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues</hi> in <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> I gueſſe one reaſon may bee, that prayers and ſermons were more acceptable then ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices.</p>
            <p>The eſpeciall offices performed in the <hi>Synagogue,</hi> were theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Man was inſtructed.</item>
               <item>God was honoured.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Inſtruction of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Arts and Armes are the equall ſupporters of great and good Kingdomes, and the one profeſſion cannot be more dangerous, then the other is labourious. <hi>Plutarch</hi> cannot reſolue whether flouriſhing <hi>Rome</hi> did owe more to the Forts &amp; Wals of <hi>Romulus,</hi> or the Schooles
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25198:10"/> and Temples of <hi>Publicola:</hi> ſurely <hi>Athens</hi> was more famous for being the nurſery of good letters, then the Metropolis of all <hi>Greece.</hi> One ſpeciall act of renowne was performed by <hi>Nero,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacit.</note> he dedicated a ſchoole as <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> noteth, hoping thereby to raiſe a monument of immortall honour to his owne name, and no maruaile, for what tongue of the eloquent can ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the merits of ſuch <hi>Heroes</hi> who haue beene Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Schooles,<note place="margin">2 Reg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.20.</note> and Patrons of good letters? beaſts may beget beaſts, a rurall Pagan may be the father of a man, but to beget, or enlighten a ſoule, is a worke onely for God,<note place="margin">Malmſ.</note> or a learned profeſſor. <hi>Henry Beuclarke</hi> was bold to tell <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, <hi>that a man without learning, was but a ſilly beaſt in a rich capariſon.</hi> The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> continued among poſterities as a ſweet oyntment poured forth, for conueying com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune waters into the City of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> with what honour ſhall wee crowne their names, who haue like <hi>Caleb</hi> bleſſed this Iland with the vpper ſprings of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred knowledge in our Vniuerſities,<note place="margin">Iudges. 1.15.</note> &amp; with the lower of humane and politer learning, in our free ſchooles throughout the kingdome? So long as there ſhall bee one leafe in any Library, ſo long as a ſtone ſhall remaine vpon a ſtone in our Colledges, ſo long as there ſhall be one man vpon the earth, let the memorie of our Founders, be as a banquet among poſterities. I am not beſides the cuſhion while in the Synagogue, I honour Arts, for whatſoeuer was in the Schoole, was after a moſt eminent manner in the Synagogue, but I haue ſtayed too long among the lower formes: Now wee may heare a diuinity lecture or a ſermon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cices.</note>As the Orator did deſire another <hi>Craſſus</hi> to deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher to the life, the excellent worth of Oratorie, ſo I confeſſe ingeniouſly, that I heartily wiſh ſome power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and eloquent <hi>Apollo,</hi> would lend mee a tongue to ſpeake the admirable, and ſoule ſauing excellency of learned and deuout ſermons.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:25198:10"/>
            <p>As euery thing of price, ſo the knowledge of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine myſteries doth require trauaile. Prayer, meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſong ſtudie, are expected in the preacher; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, deuotion, and attention in the hearer;<note place="margin">Hocker. l. 5. Ecc. Pol.</note> it is well obſerued by that Oracle of our Church, that we bring not knowledge with vs into the world, and therefore the leſſe opportunities or abilities the people haue in themſelues, the more they need the helpe, and ſhould be thankfull for the labours of learned miniſters. Chriſt was not onely the word, but a Preacher, nor did hee onely merit the crowne, but direct his Auditors in the way of euerlaſting ſaluation. I may compare good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> conducting the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of Chriſtians, to the <hi>Canaan</hi> of heauen, to the keyes of <hi>Dauid,</hi> to the ſalt whereby conuerſation is ſeaſoned,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.14. 1. Cor 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> or to light whereby the ſoule is guided: the Apoſtle hath all, <hi>It pleaſed God by preaching to ſaue them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God hath giuen the heart, and great is the number of our Synagogues; God hath giuen the word, and greater is the number of Preachers; but where is the armie of conſcionable hearers?<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> the obedient ſonne doth often viſit the houſe of his father; ſo the Saint doth frequent the earthly Manſion of his heauenly God:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Saluianus. l. 5.</hi> Spernitur Dei templum vt con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urra tur ad theatrum.</note> but may not the complaint of <hi>Saluianus</hi> bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued? <hi>The Temple of God is deſpiſed, and the ſtage more honoured, Churches are empty but Tauerns, and Brothel-houſes are throngued.</hi> A Recuſant can haue no apologie; art thou a ſinner? in the Temple thou ſhalt finde a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour; haſt thou a bleeding conſcience? here ſhalt thou finde the Balme of <hi>Gilead;</hi> art thou a Saint? here ſhalt thou find God ready to eſtabliſh thee,<note place="margin">Pſal 122.1.</note> Oh for the ſpirit of <hi>Dauid, Hee was glad when they ſaid vnto him, they would go vp to the houſe of God.</hi> The way to the Church triumphant in heauen, lyeth through the Church militant on earth. I will conclude this medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the word of <hi>Iacob</hi> which was vſually engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:25198:11"/> vpon the frontiſpice of ancient Synagogues, <hi>The Temple is the houſe of God, and the gate of heauen,</hi> the Righteous will enter in and heare what the Lord will ſay vnto him, and meditate what he ſhall ſay vnto the Lord; and that is the ſecond benefit of the Synagogue,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To honour God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In vaine ſhall the moſt cloquent <hi>Apollos</hi> touch the care of man by Sermons, vnleſſe the eare of God bee m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d for a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſing by prayers. Prayers are the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f all religious exerciſes: in ſermons God vouchſafeth to ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to man, in prayers man is admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſpeake to God; in ſermons God deſcendeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man, in prayers man aſcendeth vnto God Sermons are the ſeed from whence g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od prayers ſpring, prayers are the deaw which make ſermons flouriſh: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the two Tables, and the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Manna were in the Arke; ſo the Tables of ſermons, and the Manna of prayers, are conſerued in our Synagog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: I dare not aduenture vpon the copious diuiſion of the Apoſtle, and ſhew vnto you the difference and the excellencies,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1</note> of prayers, interceſſion, ſupplication, and thankſgiuing: onely thus.</p>
            <p>Prayers
<list>
                  <item>1 Supplicat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rie, for bleſſings to be obtained.</item>
                  <item>2 Gratulatorie, for bleſſings receiued.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt of Supplication: Supplications are the <hi>Iacobs</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather, where by the ſoule mounteth vp to heauen, they are the delight of God, and the happineſſe of man: zealouſly to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſeech, is powerfully to command; thus did <hi>Iacob wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le with the Lord, and triumph,</hi> nay <hi>the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen inuiteth, and ſuffereth violence,</hi> the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing violence of importunate, and ſtrong ſupplications. The omnipotent Maieſtie, whoſe title is inuincible, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e euer come by an Army of humble ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Would you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e vic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orious o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er your inſolent enemies? prayers are the moſt proſperous Souldiers: While <hi>Moyſes holdeth vp his hand, the troopes of Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecke
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25198:11"/> fall to the ground:</hi> let vs therefore furrow our cheekes with an inundation of teares, and beleaguer the Lord of Hoaſts with our continuall prayers, let our deuouteſt ſupplications, ſharpen the ſwords of our Souldiers, proſper the deſignes of our Commanders, beautifie the Crowne of our religious Soueraigne, and continue a roome for euery man of this Iland to ſit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his owne vine: Cry mightily vnto God, <hi>and pray inſtantly for the well faire of Ieruſalem.</hi> Would you bee bleſſed with the pardon of your ſinnes, with the hidden Manna of a peacefull conſcience, with a crowne of eternall glory, or with what euer the magnificent hand of God can conferre? Prayer is the price, and the Temple the houſe of prayer.<note place="margin">Pſal. 48.9.</note> 
               <hi>We will pray and wayt for the louing kindneſſe of our God in the midſt of his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now of Thankſgiuing: in the Temple euery man ſpeaketh of the praiſe of God, and no maruaile, for as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> largely, <hi>No penne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ep. 32. it. ep 77.</note> 
               <hi>no tongue can bee better employed, then in expreſſing, no heart, no ſoule then in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, the great debt of our thankefulneſſe vnto God:</hi> ſuch and ſo infinite is the bounty of our God, that night and day with bended knees, inflamed hearts, and wel tuned tongues,<note place="margin">Arnob. l. 1.</note> we ought to pay the hourely tribute of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouteſt praiſes: What can God do more, then crowne man with louing kindneſſe? what can man do leſſe, then exalt God with thankfulneſſe? no man ſo poore but he may, no man ſo great but hee ſhould offer this cheape, yet pretious incenſe. To this end Altars, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Synagogues, Churches are rayſed; to this end man and Angels created, that God may receiue the glory of praiſes: <hi>In all things giue thankes,</hi> for,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.18</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was our Synagogue builded. Apply.</p>
            <p>The building is a Synagogue. It is not onely law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but commendable, to call vpon and praiſe the name of God in our priuate families, and ſecret cloſets; but the greateſt bleſſings do accompanie the ſacrifices of a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25198:12"/> Synagogue, that is a Congregation. The Lord is in his glory when he is incloſed with the greateſt multitude of petitioners, <hi>Oh that men would praiſe the Lord in the aſſembly of the Elders,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.32.</note> 
               <hi>in the midſt of the Synagogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, each ſoule ſhould be a liuing, &amp; a holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: God indeed is the Lord of heauen and earth, and needeth not to borrow a Synagogue or houſe made with hands,<note place="margin">Act. 17.24, 35.</note> his chiefe delight is to keepe his Court with thoſe, the Chappels of whoſe ſoules are beſt adorned with charity and holineſſe, <hi>Know you not that your bodies are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> It is the ſcandall of our times, that ſome Churches haue beene turned into ſtables, this gangrene is inlarged, and the Temples of our ſoules are become the Augean ſtables of all ſinnefull filthineſſe; the drunkard tranſlateth his temple into a ſwine-ſtyue, the wanton his into a ſtew, the couetous his into a denne of theeues, the prophane ſwearer his into an ordinary or dycing Roome, where you ſhall heare no other language but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> oathes; euery notorious ſinner is a ſacrilegious po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tor, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer of this ſpirituall Synagogue, fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d by the founder of heauen and earth. I conclude, <hi>Yee are the temple of the liuing God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.16.</note> I ſhall pray that God may pleaſe to dwell with you, to walke in you, that hee may be our God, and we his people.</p>
            <p>Now behold the Templer, for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the hungerpined onely to behold plentifull and delicately furniſhed tables, or for the extreamely indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent onely to gaze vpon huge maſſes of treaſure, might rather proue a torment, then a comfort: come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now and let vs behold, the bleſſed vnion of the Centurions magnificence, and our happineſſe. We, we are the heires of this ſacred and ample bounty, Hee hath built <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> a Synagogue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.]</hi> The end giueth glory to the action, and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth happineſſe to the agent: lauiſh expenſes cannot entitle a man liberall, nor raſh boldneſſe ſtile any man
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25198:12"/> valiant; for inconſiderate ruſhing into dangers is a frenzy, and profuſe caſting away of treaſures, is fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique prodigality: that bountie is moſt honourable, which hath the largeſt, and moſt religious obiect. Hee ſheweth his bounty to man, and his piety towards God moſt happily, who doth erect a Synagogue for the people of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> hath a foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold relation.
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Vs</hi> Enemies.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Vs</hi> Captiues.</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> Strangers.</item>
                  <item>4 <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> Of the True Church.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who was not a voluntary vaſſall, was reputed an enemie to the <hi>Roman</hi> State, the greater farre the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our Centurion, to ſo peruerſe, ſo <hi>Iewiſh</hi> an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie: friendſhip and kindred make too ſtreight a ſpheare for charity to moue in;<note place="margin">Omnes odit, qui malos odit. Aug. ep.</note> for he ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſcarſely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect any, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho embraceth only thoſe to whom he is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged by merit or by blood: let the memory of this Captaine be as an oyntment powred forth, he knew as well how to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ercome in loue, as to conquer with the ſword.<note place="margin">Math. 5.43.</note> The <hi>Iewes</hi> eſteemed it lawfull policy to hate their Enemies, but our Centurion was not ſowred with this leuen of their doctrine, nor infected with their practiſe; it may be he had obſerued, that the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable ſunne did impart her cheriſhing beames vnto the good and bad, and that light he would follow; hee is an Angell rather then a man, that can ouercome euill with good; it was an act (I had almoſt ſaid) able to make, ſurely to ſnew a God, <hi>To loue an enemie,</hi> ſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle of our God of loue,<note place="margin">Math. 5.44.</note> 
               <hi>Hee loued vs when wee were enemies:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mitate the Lord Ieſus, <hi>Bleſſe them that curſe you, Loue them that hate you, for this is to be a Son of God,</hi> and a follower of our Centurion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vs Captiues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miſery and infamy are linked together in the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues chaine; nor is it ſo much pittie, as pride or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25198:13"/> that doth continue life vnto the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; it was the barbarous c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtome of the inſulting <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> to driue thoſe who their ſword had ſubdued, by herds through their City as the ſport, and ſcorne of women and children, then to ſell them as beaſts, or which was the greater curteſie, becauſe the ſhorter tragedy, to caſt them to the beaſts, tumble them into the ſea, or ſet them at liberty by ſome other death: but it ſeemeth our Centurion was truly valiant, who neuer knew enemy but in the field, nor vſed other bonds in the City, but loue, nor other priſon, but a Synagogue. Proper is the doctrine of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine, We are all mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that large body of mankind, theſe louely titles of neighbour or brother, are not built ſo much vpon conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, or ſimilitude of ſhape, as vpon the image of God engrauen in our reaſonable ſoule: Haue pitty vpon thoſe who are in bonds. Be kindly affectionated one towards an other.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s Strangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True charity ſcarſe knoweth the name of ſtranger; all are brothers, all children or fellow members in her regiſter:<note place="margin">Inuiſum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum genus Tacit.</note> ſhe doth guide the eye, and temper the heart of our Centurion. The <hi>Iewes</hi> are deſeruedly called, <hi>a Nation hated by all, becauſe ſpitefull to al;</hi> they eſteemed all other people as baſtards, and others reputed them as rebels: but ſee, no peruerſeneſſe of nature, no iealouſie of rebellion, no nor that exaſperating name of <hi>Iew,</hi> can abate the edge of truly compaſſionate loue; Parity in condition ſhould rayſe a mutuall tenderneſſe in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we are all ſtrangers, and without treaſon it may be printed, Emperors and Kings are but ſoiourners euen in their owne dominions: Let not our loue bee eſtranged from them, who are of a ſtrange Nation. <hi>entertaine ſtrangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 13.2.</note>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s the people of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As yet the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Synagogue, was a true Church, and the ſonnes of <hi>Iacob,</hi> the royall Prieſt-hood; happy therefore that zeale, which did expreſſe piety toward
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25198:13"/> God, in magnificent fauours vpon Gods people. Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath her name for vniting mens conſciences &amp; affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; nor can there be a fayrer euidence of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then loue to the Church.<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.3.</note> 
               <hi>All my delight is vpon the Saints,</hi> was <hi>Dauids</hi> note, and his temples could take no reſt, vntill a place was found for the habitation of God. Brethren, loue you God? honour his ſeruants, repaire and beautifie his temples: the farewell of our Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion, reuiueth that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Doe good to all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>but eſpecially to the houſe, and houſehold of faith:</hi> for this is to loue the people of God, and to build a Synagogue.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Roman</hi> Captaine is now diſcharged, and if euer he had a parallell, hee muſt bee rayſed from our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Centurion, from THOMAS SVITON, our magnificent, and ſole founder.</p>
            <p>Thankefully to commend vnto poſterity,<note place="margin">Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration.</note> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous acts of deceaſed Worthies, is an office, of as true gratitude, as great and venerable antiquity: Come therefore now, &amp; let vs triumph ouer thoſe commune enemies of eminent goodneſſe, <hi>Ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rance,</hi> and <hi>Enuy:</hi> Were it a point of the ſame facility, to bury in obliui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to locke vp in ſilence, the ineffable magnificence of our SVTTON, the Auditor or Reader ſhould haue had no ſubiect of his criticks from my tongue or pen. but to forget SVTTON totally, is as impoſſible as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe him fully; you ſhall therefore cenſure me, ſo you will honour him: my neuer yet practiſed Panygyricall veine, is more poore in relation to his worth, then my eleemoſinary ſtate in compariſon of his wealth. <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> ſhall bee my pleader in his prologue to <hi>Agricola,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacit.</note> 
               <hi>Commend and admire others, Pardon me,</hi> while I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to awake our bleſſed Founder, and lead him through the fiue roomes of my text; firſt you ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer, Who and what our Founder is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He]</hi> The builder of the Synagogue a Centurion, our Founder more, a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of the Ordnance, a Gentleman of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25198:14"/> Ancient deſcent, of liberall education, a man rich in Arts, &amp; famous in Armes; for the former, he was ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced in good letters, that he appeared the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat man of his times, for diſcharging the office of a learned, wiſe, and able Secretary to the moſt Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Peeres of this Nation; and what abilitie hee had ſucked from the Vniuerſity in ſpeculation, he did with credit practiſe vnder famous <hi>Warwicke,</hi> and great <hi>Leiceſter.</hi> Theſe were the firſt paths that lead to <hi>Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> greatneſſe, and our happineſſe: for his other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours from Armes, if you obſerue the time of our Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turions imployment in the field, you may know, there was a time when forraigne religion was the patroneſſe of domeſticke rebellion; when two Northerne and ſuperſtitious Earles durſt diſplay the <hi>Romiſh</hi> enſigne againſt inuincible <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> then, then was this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſonne of <hi>Pallas</hi> aduanced to the command of the Ordnance, and gaue a happy probatum of his loyalty, valour, and wiſedome; here I ſuppoſe hee learned to honour, and reſolued to cheriſh Military men; but you will enquire from what myne his infinite treaſures did ariſe: I can informe you, from proſperous merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing, from the great farme of all the mynes about <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and from the wiſedome of his vertuous fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gality: of his perſon I will conclude, in the enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium of <hi>Pammachius</hi> framed by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ierome:</hi>
               <note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eemoſynis diues humi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mis. Ier ad Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machium de obitu vxer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Sutton</hi> was gentyle by birth, high by humility and which is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt honour, Rich by charitable b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unty:</p>
            <p>Now to his building, <hi>He built.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was a great and good builder, not ſo much for his owne priuate, as for the publike; his treaſures were not lauiſhed in rayſing a Towre to his owne name, or erecting ſtately Pallaces for his owne pompe and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: the ſuſtaining of liuing temples, the endowing of Colledges, the enriching of Corporations, the building Cauſwayes, and repairing of high-wayes; Aboue all, the foundation of King <hi>Iames</hi> his Hoſpitall at his ſole
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25198:14"/> and proper charge, were the happy monuments of his architecture, ſurely this was to bee a Mogarenſis in the beſt ſenſe, that is to build for euer. Hee did fulfill the letter of the Apoſtle in building <hi>Gold, Siluer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Peruſe our Founders Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</note> 
               <hi>and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſtones;</hi> for he commanded Plate and Iewels to bee ſold, and conuerted into money for the expediting of our Hoſpitall.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not mention thouſands conferred vpon friends, and ſeruants; but theſe legacies enſuing merit a laſting memory: in the renowned Vniuerſity of <hi>Camb.</hi> to <hi>Ieſus</hi> Colledge 500 Markes, to <hi>Magdalen</hi> 500 pound, for the redemption of priſoners in <hi>London</hi> 200 pound, for the encouragement of Merchants 1000 pound to bee lent gratis vnto tenne beginners; nor was his charity confined within theſe ſeas, but that Weſterne <hi>Troy,</hi> ſtout <hi>Oſtend</hi> ſhall receiue 100 pound for the reliefe of the poore from his fountaine;<note place="margin">To truſt the Miniſter is to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nour him.</note> in all theſe his piety was very laudable, for in many of theſe acts of bounty, his prime repoſe was in the conſcionable integrety of the Prieſt, in thoſe places where he ſowed his benefits, certes this was to build as high as heauen: now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue his expedition.</p>
            <p>He <hi>Hath</hi> built.</p>
            <p>Expedition is commendable in laudable enterprizes, and euen in this our Founder had his honour: While his Wife liued, his houſe was an open Hoſpitall, and when ſhe expired, he was frugall in his owne family, that he might proue the more magnificent to many. <hi>Origen</hi> perſwadeth that our Sauiours aduiſe, <hi>to leaue all,</hi> had not ſo full an ayme at the effect, as the affection; and herein our Founder merited ample honour, for if any queſtionod him, where he would employ his great eſtate, his diuine and conſtant reply was, <hi>that his bread muſt be caſt vpon the waters.</hi> i. vpon the watery cheeks of the neglected poore: Moreouer hee procured an Act of Parleament for a Mortmaine, for the eſtablſhing of an intended Hoſpitall in <hi>Halling-bury</hi> in the County
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25198:15"/> of <hi>Eſſex;</hi> but a more noble Spirit prompting him to reſtore that <hi>Charterhouſe</hi> to true religion, which was formerly ſacrificed to ſuperſtition,<note place="margin">Suttons caſe by Sir Ed.</note> he became an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſutor to King <hi>Iames</hi> of bleſſed memory, to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to be the Royall God-father of this royall founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; whereunto that learned, letters, and Scholler lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing King,<note place="margin">Cooke. Founders wil.</note> did gratiouſly condeſcend, and confirmed our Founders bounty vpon vs by his Letters Patent, and the broad Seale, this being done, memorable <hi>Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> chargeth, nay adiureth his Executors and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers, as they ſhall anſwer before the tribunall of Ieſus Chriſt, that they imploy their beſt endeauours, in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening, and reducing into act his intended charity; would you heare more? I haue it from honourable authority, that if the thred of our Founders life had beene continued ſomewhat longer, his vote and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was, to haue beene the good Maſter, of our great Society. So much for expedition: Now view the</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Synagogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Foundation may be eſteemed rather a glorious Temple them a Synagogue, and rather a City then a Temple; but I will not ſteppe beyond my bounds: in a Synagogue we found formerly, <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion:</hi> for deuotion, thoſe reuerend heires of our Founders magnificence twice euery day viſit our Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, and aſcend in ſoule to heauen by zealous prayers, and vnfained thankſgiuings; ſuch is our ſtrict obſeruance of the daily ſeruice, that wee may ſeeme neerer vnto the Cathedrall, then the parochiall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; on the Lords day, Ieſus is faithfully, though plainly preached in our Synagogue. For inſtruction, here ingenuous children do daily ſit at the feet of their learned teachers; but of theſe heerafter: Wee finde in the ſacred Oracles a frequent mention of Maſters of Synagogues.</p>
            <p>The great Maſter of our Synagogue is fixed vpon the moſt honoured grandies of our State, and the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25198:15"/> moſt reuerend Prelates of our Church, they who ſit at the Helme of our kingdome, are gratiouſly pleaſed to ſteere &amp; guide the goodly Shippe of renowned <hi>Suttons</hi> charity; and here wee may note the wiſedome of our Founder, who made choyſe of ſuch honourable and powerfull gouernors, who were able and ready to maintaine his bequeſt, and honour his foundation: it is the glory of our noble gouernors, and the happineſſe of our Society, that no cunning aduocate, no greedy Lord, could vndermine our foundation; and what was nobly begunne, is honourably continued by them, for father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and mercifull iuſtice, let no Court, no ſtate compare with our gouernment. All, all deſerue our thankes to them, &amp; our hearty prayers for them, the poore ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard ſhall, and the religious flocke muſt importune God for a bleſſing vpon them,<note place="margin">Great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours &amp; good manners con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed.</note> by whoſe wiſedome and goodneſſe, many bleſſings are conueyed vnto vs: the Vicegerent of this grand Maſter, is the right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>R, D.</hi> Knight, whoſe prouidence hath adorned our Chappell with Organs, and beautifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the walkes and ſeuerall roomes of our ample foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.<note place="margin">Relinquet marmoriam.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now obſerue the Members of this Synagogue.</p>
            <p>For <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our body hath one Maſter</p>
            <p>Seuerall Officers, as Preacher, &amp;c. of whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution you may read at large, in <hi>Suttons</hi> Caſe,<note place="margin">Suttons Caſe.</note> Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by one of our Gouernors, Sir <hi>Edward Cooke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seuerall cohabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting members,
<list>
                  <item>Aged men who haue hazarded their blood, or impaired their ſtate by warres, or ſuffered loſſe by Sea, foureſcore.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:25198:16"/>
            <p>Seuerall cohabiting members.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Hopefull children carefully inſtructed in the learned tongues, and humane Arts, lecently cloathed, plentifully dyeted, &amp; connueniently lodged, 40</item>
            </list>
            <p>Beſides theſe, The faithfull prouidence of Sir <hi>Rich. Sutton</hi> Knight, hath purchaſed lands from whence twenty foure Academians re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue annuall penſions in both our renowned Vniuerſities.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Here is a Proteſtant.</note>Briefely — very nigh two hundred daily feed vpon our <hi>Suttons</hi> bounty.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with the charge of <hi>Darius,</hi> Day by Day we haue our portion without faile,<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra 6.9.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may offer ſacrifices of ſweet ſauour vnto the God of heauen, and pray for the life of our religious Prince and Patrone King <hi>Charles:</hi> and thus do we pray,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O thou King of Kings, cloath all our Soueraignes ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies with ſhame, but vpon his head let the Crowne flouriſh; mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his raigne proſperous on earth, and glorious in heauen; make this foundation a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ynagogue of deuout men, ſeruing thee in all peace and holineſſe ſo long as the Sunne and Moone ſhall endure, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, To whom with the Father and the holy Spirit, all power, maieſty, mercy, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and bleſſing be aſcribed for euer and for euer, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="list_of_names">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:25198:16"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of the names of the Right Honorable, Right Reuerend, and Right Worthy Gouernors of King <hi>James</hi> his Hoſpitoll, founded by <hi>Thomas Sutton</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <p>The moſt Reuerend Father in God, the Lord Arch Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> his Grace, Surui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ouer-ſeer.</p>
            <p>The Right Honourable
<list>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Couentrie,</hi> Lord Keeper.</item>
                  <item>Lord Priuy Seale, Earle of <hi>Mancheſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord Steward, Earle of <hi>Penbroke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>L<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Chamberlaine, Earle of <hi>Mongomery</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Right Reuerend
<list>
                  <item>Lord Biſhop of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord Biſhop of <hi>Ely.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Right Worſhipful
<list>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Edward Coke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Randolph Crew.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Robert Heath,</hi> his Maieſties Atturny generall.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Henry Martine,</hi> Deane of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udge of the Admiraltie.</item>
                  <item>Doctor <hi>Donne,</hi> Deane of <hi>Pauls.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Sir <hi>Richard Sutton,</hi> Suruiuing Executor.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Robert Dallington,</hi> Maſter.</item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Browne</hi> Eſquier.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:25198:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25198:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
